"After unusual warmth, Arctic sea ice hits new record low for February"
Alaska Dispatch News
"March 2, 2016 Wednesday"
"Copyright 2016 Alaska Dispatch Publishing, LLC All Rights Reserved"
Section: NEWS; Arctic
Length: 351 words
"Highlight: Temeratures in the Arctic were well above historical average for February and at one oint sea ice growth stalled for several weeks, en route to setting a new record for the lowest average sea ice extent ever recorded in  that month."
Body
"Arctic sea ice reached another record last month, posting the lowest average February extent since satellite"
"records began in 1979, scientists said on Wednesday."
Sea ice extent -- defined as the area where ice covers at least 15 percent of the sea surface -- averaged 5.48
"million  square  miles over  the  month,  about  7.7 percent  lower  than  the  average  long-term  February  extent measured from 1981 to 2010, the said in its ."
The February record follows .
Sea ice usually begins to form in late September and peaks in early or mid-March before the annual melt season
starts.
"But this year, the growth has been slower than in the past, with . The ice rebounded a bit late in the month, largely"
"thanks to a growth spurt in Russia's Sea of Okhotsk, but was still much lower than normal at the start of March. The"
"late ice is low in concentration, according to NSIDC data, and expected to disappear quickly once the melt season starts."
"The February stall is part of a wider trend of reduced sea-ice extent in winter, a season that once saw nearly"
"all marine waters in the Arctic frozen over. Last year's annual maximum of 5.61 million square miles, reached on Feb. 25, 2015, was the ."
"Unusual warmth across the Arctic is blamed for the slow ice growth this winter, the NSIDC said in its report. It cited"
"that found average February air temperatures over the Beaufort Sea, Chukchi Sea and central Arctic Ocean were about 9 degrees higher than the 2003-2015 average. Warmth was especially notable near the North Pole, the center said. February temperatures over the central Arctic Ocean were 11 to 14 degrees above 1981-2010 average"
"for the month, the center said."
"Winter ice freezeup was late, lagging by a full two months in the Kara and Barents seas, the center said. Ice also"
"formed late in other parts of the Arctic -- the Beaufort, Chukchi, East Siberian and Laptev seas -- between 10 and 40 days later than the average, the center said."
"After unusual warmth, Arctic sea ice hits new record low for February"
Page 2 of 2
Graphic
See image link
Sea ice in Norton Bay in March of 2011.
Stephen Nowers photo
"Load-Date: March 3, 2016"
End of Document
