Arctic sea ice annual minimum is 6th lowest on satellite record
Alaska Dispatch News
"October 7, 2014 Tuesday"
"Copyright 2014 Alaska Dispatch Publishing, LLC All Rights Reserved"
Section: NEWS; Arctic
Length: 424 words
"Highlight: Arctic sea ice has ceased its annual melt and begun re-freezing as winter returns to the northern hemishere. This year's sea-ice extent was the sixth-lowest on the satellite record, researchers said."
Body
Arctic sea ice has started to reform after reaching what appears to be an annual minimum that was the sixth-lowest
"on satellite record, the  said on Monday."
"Sea-ice  (1.94 million square miles) Wednesday, slightly below the minimum reached last year and well below the"
"average recorded from 1981 to 2010, according to the NSIDC. This year's ice minimum was well above the record minimum of 3.41 million square kilometers in 2012, according to NSIDC data."
"Sea-ice patterns this year have been uneven across the Arctic, with vast stretches of open water off northern"
"Alaska and eastern Siberia but relatively more  ice in the Barents and Kara  Seas north of Western Europe, according to the Boulder-based NSIDC."
"""The most notable feature was the lack of ice north of the Laptev Sea that at one point in the melt season extended"
"beyond 85 degrees north latitude, within 550 kilometers (342 miles) of the North Pole,"" the NSIDC said in a statement."
"The , the marine passage from Bering Strait across the top of Russia, was clear this summer. But the alternate"
"shipping route, the Northwest Passage -- which runs from the North Atlantic through the Canadian Archipelago in Canada's eastern Arctic region -- was blocked by ice."
The NSIDC considers areas of the Arctic with at least 15 percent sea ice to be ice-covered. The center measures
"surface coverage by satellite; coverage statistics do not account for ice age or thickness, but the NSIDC and other organizations, including NASA, monitor those factors as well. NASA is studying Arctic ice and its connection to atmospheric conditions in a program called , for Arctic Radiation IceBridge Sea and Ice Experiment."
"While there is more September sea ice now than two years ago, coverage is remarkably low, considering other"
"factors, said a NASA scientist."
"""The summer started off relatively cool and lacked the big storms or persistent winds that can break up ice and"
"increase melting,"" Walter Meier, a research scientist at NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center, said in a statement"
"issued by the space agency. ""Even with a relatively cool year, the ice is so much thinner than it used to be. It's more susceptible to melting."""
Arctic sea ice annual minimum is 6th lowest on satellite record
Page 2 of 2
"Arctic ice cover had grown back to 5.087 million square kilometers as of Sunday, according to the NSIDC, but it is"
"possible that freeze-up will be interrupted by weather patterns. A shift in wind or an unusual late-season melt could reduce ice coverage briefly, the center said."
Graphic
See image link
"Lots of people think of the Arctic as just a flat expanse of white. This couldn't be further from the truth. There are all sorts of cracks (leads) and mountains (ridges), similar to tectonic plates."
NASA photo
"Load-Date: October 7, 2014"
End of Document
